[Music]
how much
is a human life worth
ideally we'd like to think there's no
price tag i mean each precious life is
of inestimable value
but there are limited resources and
policy decisions to be made which leads
to
fascinating papers like this
the cost effectiveness of 500
life-saving interventions
587 to be exact with some costing more
than 10
billion dollars per year of life saved
overall the average intervention costs
forty-two thousand dollars which is how
much it costs to save a year of
someone's life putting flashing lights
at railroad crossings so how could you
justify not installing them well you
could save more lives with the same
money if you had a grooved pavement on
highways but if you really cared about
saving drivers you could save nearly a
hundred times more lives investing the
same money in media campaigns to
encourage people to wear their seat
belts but if you really want value if
you want to prevent bangs for the least
bucks
there are some interventions that save
more resources than they cost
yeah most interventions cost 10 000 or
more per year of life saved but check
out these they're not just cost neutral
they mean you can save lives by saving
money target about low-hanging fruit
studies for example suggest workplace
wellness programs can generate savings
not just saving more than your spending
but potentially tripling your money by
investing in wellness
but since employee participation is
almost always voluntary this introduces
the specter of selection bias where
healthier people are just drawn to
wellness programs in the first place and
indeed
during the year prior to a wellness
intervention those who would later sign
up already had lower medical
expenditures and healthier behaviors
than future non-participants so no
wonder they could end up doing better
than their non-participating colleagues
even if the wellness program had zero
benefit
thankfully there are an increased number
of randomized controlled trials of
wellness programs to see if we can prove
cause and effect to answer the question
do workplace health promotion programs
work particularly important given that
the workplace wellness industry is now a
multi-billion dollar industry
one of the most recent randomized
controlled trials was published in the
journal of the american medical
association thousands of employees were
effectively randomized to a workplace
wellness program at bj's wholesale club
and although program participants
reported they were engaging more
positive health behaviors such as
getting regular exercise there was no
significant differences in clinical
measures of health or health care
spending and utilization
the author suggested we may have to
temper our expectations about the
financial return on investment that
wellness programs can deliver
at least in the short term
now some argue that even a break even
program that is one that does not impose
additional cost to the company but
produces significant population health
improvement might be a worthy investment
but perhaps the growing evidence that
demonstrates limited or no concrete
wellness program effects should
encourage wellness companies and
employers to critically assess the
programs and try to improve them in a
survey of 162 company wellness programs
for example only a third
offered nutrition counseling and even
with counseling it's more than simply
trying to convince people to take better
care of themselves it requires that the
organization creates an environment
where leading a healthy lifestyle is the
default option what are they promoting
in the company cafeteria for example
what's being served up at meetings and
in vending machines yeah a lifestyle
management program at pepsico failed to
save the company money but somehow i
doubt one of the components of pepsico's
wellness program healthy living was
telling employees not to eat or drink
any of their own products
in fact if you go back to that bj's case
yes a few percentages more employees
said they were more regularly exercising
but when it came to nutrition it was a
complete flop in terms of things like
drinking less soda or more fruits and
vegetables no wonder their health hardly
budged
in a systematic review of systematic
reviews on the effectiveness of dietary
workplace interventions the average
improvement in fruit and vegetable
intake combined was
0.7 portions a day no wonder these
programs aren't doing better in wealth
of nations adam smith wrote that workers
are less likely to be productive when
they are frequently sick than when they
are generally in good health sickness
cannot fail to diminish the produce of
their industry
maybe they just need more produce than
0.7 servings a day
[Music]
you